The highest respect
Ogromny szacunek
To our teacher
Do naszych nauczycieli
-Time has elapsed... -Mao!
- Czas minął... - Mao!
Do that in the music room.
Idź do pokoju muzycznego.
The concert band is using it.
Zespół tam ćwiczy.
Then do it at home.
To do domu.
But we have a singing test tomorrow. Don't you guys need to practice?
Jutro mamy test ze śpiewu. Nie chcecie poćwiczyć?
Practicing now won't help.
Już na to za późno.
What? Mei, how can I get better?
Co? To co mam zrobić?
How should I know?
Skąd mam wiedzieć?
Mana.
Mana.
Why don't you do it like Shiho and lie? "I can't talk."
Weź przykład z Shiho i udawaj, że nie umiesz mówić.
She's lying?
Shiho udaje?
I don't know. But it seems suspicious.
Nie wiem, ale to podejrzane.
I'll admit, it is strange that she can't speak for two weeks.
Przyznaję, to dziwne, że od dwóch tygodni nie może mówić.
Cut it out!
Przestańcie!
I think she's telling the truth.
Myślę, że nie udaje.
You know, I think our class is cursed.
Nasza klasa chyba jest przeklęta.
What?
Co?
I mean, Mr. Hayashi suddenly quit too.
Pan Hayashi nagle odszedł.
Why did he have to quit anyway?
Właściwie dlaczego?
I don't know.
Nie wiem.
Nobody knows the real reason.
Nikt nie zna prawdziwego powodu.
See, I told you we're cursed.
Widzicie, to klątwa.
That's not funny.
To nie jest zabawne.
But weird stuff keeps happening.
Ale ciągle dzieje się coś dziwnego.
Shiho can't talk and Miho disappeared.
Shiho nie mówi, Miho zniknęła.
What? Didn't Miho's family skip town?
Co? Jej rodzina nie wyjechała?
No way!
Niemożliwe!
I heard she transferred to a school abroad.
Słyszałam, że wyjechała za granicę do szkoły.
Isn't she dead? Someone said that, too.
A nie umarła? To też słyszałam.
That's just what you want, Mao.
Chciałabyś, Mao.
Oh, cut it out.
Przestań.
Disgusting Pig! Rich Bitch! Nobody Likes You!
Obrzydliwa świnia! Bogata suka! Nikt cię nie lubi!
What is with you?
Co z tobą?
Were you lying the whole time?
Cały czas udawałaś?
I know you can talk! Say something!
Wiedziałam, że możesz mówić. Powiedz coś!
Shiho!
Shiho!
I've had it!
Mam tego dość!
Memi!
Memi!
-Mana was vanished because of Shiho. -I know.
- Mana zniknęła przez Shiho. - Wiem.
But we need to ask Shiho about what Mana said to her.
Ale Shiho musi nam powiedzieć, czego dowiedziała się od Many.
Shiho, tell us the truth.
Shiho, powiedz prawdę.
If you tell us honestly, I won't get angry.
Jeśli będziesz szczera, nie będę zła.
I'm not lying.
Nie udawałam.
What?
Co?
You're such a liar!
Jak to nie?
Listen to her.
Wysłuchaj jej.
I really did lose my voice.
Naprawdę straciłam głos.
The first month, at least.
Na jakiś miesiąc.
The first month?
Miesiąc?
You were lying after that?
A potem udawałaś?
See! I told you she was lying.
Widzicie? Mówiłam!
She's a big liar!
Co za kłamczucha!
Hey, you liar! Say something!
Powiedz coś, oszustko!
Are you Okazaki's new girlfriend, Shiho?
Jesteś nową dziewczyną Okazakiego, Shiho?
Please! Tell us! This is important!
Powiedz nam! To ważne!
What?
Co?
Is it really that important?
To naprawdę takie ważne?
-Yes, is it? -Yes, it's really important!
- Chyba. - Bardzo ważne!
If it is true,
Jeśli to prawda...
then Miho is probably behind this.
to pewnie Miho nas tu zamknęła.
Revenge on the cheating woman?
Zemsta zdradzonej dziewczyny?
So, if Shiho apologizes, we will be released?
Czyli jeśli Shiho przeprosi, Miho nas wypuści?
I think it's possible.
To możliwe.
Miho was
Miho naprawdę...
really in love with Okazaki after all.
kochała Okazakiego.
Hold on.
Czekajcie.
Would she do this because someone stole her boyfriend?
Zrobiłaby coś takiego z powodu chłopaka?
That's not the only reason.
To nie jedyny powód.
This room
W tym pokoju...
seems to have a lot of medical equipment.
jest sporo sprzętu medycznego.
Because Okazaki was a doctor?
Bo Okazaki był lekarzem?
Anyway, Shiho,
Tak czy siak, Shiho,
if it's true about you and Okazaki, then apologize to Miho!
jeśli to prawda, przeproś Miho!
That's right!
Właśnie!
Hurry up and apologize!
Szybko, przeproś!
"I'm sorry I stole your boyfriend."
Powiedz: „Przepraszam, że ukradłam ci chłopaka”.
I didn't.
Nie zrobiłam tego.
I didn't steal him.
Nie zabrałam jej chłopaka.
We started dating
Zaczęliśmy się spotykać
after he and Miho broke up.
już po ich rozstaniu.
After the barbecue, he started texting me.
Po grillu zaczął do mnie pisać.
I ignored him.
Na początku go ignorowałam.
I mean,
Bałabym się...
if I stole Miho's boyfriend, who knew what she might do?
odbić Miho chłopaka. Kto wie, jak by zareagowała?
What? You think you're that pretty?
Co? Myślisz, że jesteś aż tak ładna?
Forget about that.
To nie ma znaczenia.
Listen to her.
Nie przerywaj jej.
Then he said he broke up with Miho, so he wanted to date me.
Potem powiedział, że zerwał z Miho i chce być ze mną.
When was that?
Kiedy to było?
About when everyone started to bully Miho.
Gdy wszyscy zaczęli dręczyć Miho.
Are you saying the bullying and your dating are related?
Te dwie rzeczy mają ze sobą jakiś związek?
I mean,
No bo...
since everyone was bullying her,
skoro i tak wszyscy ją nękali...
I thought I should do something too.
pomyślałam, że też coś zrobię.
You're crazy.
Zwariowałaś.
What a bitch.
Ale z ciebie suka.
You're so full of yourself just because you're cute.
Jesteś tak pewna siebie, bo masz w miarę ładną twarz.
Apologize to Miho!
Przeproś Miho!
That's right. Apologize, you slut!
Właśnie. Przeproś ją, dziwko!
You're wrong. It's not Miho.
Mylicie się. To nie Miho.
Miho isn't doing this!
To nie ona za tym stoi!
Not that again?
Znowu to samo?
"The culprit isn't Miho".
„Miho nie jest sprawcą”.
I've had it with you!
Mam tego dość!
Kyoko!
Kyoko!
What do you mean by that, Shiho?
Co masz na myśli, Shiho?
Miho isn't doing this.
To nie Miho.
I mean...
Chodzi o to, że...
Miho...
Miho...
Hurry up and say it!
No już, wyduś to z siebie!
Keep talking, Shiho.
Mów dalej, Shiho.
I mean, Miho is...
Miho...
dead.
nie żyje.
What?
Co?
Don't say that, even if you're joking!
Nawet tak nie żartuj!
Miho...
Miho...
killed herself.
popełniła samobójstwo.
Everything you're saying and doing doesn't make sense.
Zupełnie nie rozumiem tego, co mówisz i robisz.
Why are you lying?
Dlaczego kłamiesz?
It's not a lie.
Nie kłamię.
She texted me.
Napisała do mnie.
Out of the blue, she sent me a photo of the harbor.
Ni z tego, ni z owego wysłała mi zdjęcie nabrzeża.
She said, "I'm going to die now."
Napisała: „Teraz umrę”.
That's a lie!
Kłamiesz!
When was that?
Kiedy to było?
At the beginning of December.
Na początku grudnia.
That's about when Miho stopped coming to school.
To wtedy Miho przestała chodzić do szkoły.
Yes.
Tak.
And...
No i...
when Shiho stopped talking.
wtedy Shiho przestała mówić.
This is crazy.
To szaleństwo.
At first, I thought she was joking.
Na początku uznałam to za żart.
But...
Ale...
then I got a bad feeling.
nabrałam złych przeczuć.
I texted her back, but...
Odpisałam jej, ale...
it was never marked "read".
nigdy nie odczytała wiadomości.
Show me your phone.
Pokaż mi telefon.
-But... -Just let me see.
- Ale... - Pokaż.
The battery is dead.
Bateria padła.
She never read it.
Nigdy jej nie odczytała.
I was scared, so I went there.
Bałam się, więc tam poszłam.
Where the photo was taken.
W miejsce ze zdjęcia.
And?
I co było dalej?
Then...
Wtedy...
at the end of the pier...
na końcu mola...
Calm down, Shiho.
Uspokój się, Shiho.
It's all right, okay?
Wszystko będzie dobrze.
Right at the very edge
Na samej krawędzi mola
was just Miho's wheelchair.
stał wózek Miho.
But you didn't see her jump in, right?
Ale nie widziałaś, jak skacze, prawda?
It must be a prank.
To musiał być żart.
She probably did it to get back at you.
Pewnie chciała się na tobie odegrać.
Why would she commit suicide?
Czemu miałaby się zabić?
But she hasn't been to school once since then.
Ale nie pojawiła się już w szkole.
Has anyone seen Miho since December?
Czy ktokolwiek widział Miho od grudnia?
Maybe she really...
Może naprawdę...
Quit talking about this!
Nie mówmy o tym!
It has to be a lie.
To musi być kłamstwo.
Are you all crazy?
Zwariowałyście?
She lied that she couldn't talk,
Kłamała, że nie może mówić,
so why are you believing her now?
więc czemu teraz jej wierzycie?
If, by chance...
Jeśli faktycznie...
Although, I don't believe it at all!
Choć wcale w to nie wierzę!
But if...
Ale...
But if Miho wanted to commit suicide...
jeśli Miho naprawdę chciała się zabić...
why would she text that to Shiho?
czemu miałaby pisać o tym do Shiho?
It's too important for that.
To zbyt ważne.
Why Shiho and not me?
Czemu do Shiho, a nie do mnie?
Now that you mention it.
Faktycznie.
Miho and Shiho never really got along that well.
Miho i Shiho nigdy się nie dogadywały.
Wasn't it because she stole her boyfriend?
A nie chodziło o chłopaka?
Miho would never die over something like that!
Miho nie zabiłaby się z takiego powodu!
Everything Shiho said is a total lie!
Shiho kłamie!
I'm sorry.
Przepraszam.
It's my fault.
To moja wina.
But I never imagined she would die.
Ale nie sądziłam, że naprawdę się zabije.
The day before she texted me that she would die,
Dzień przed wysłaniem wiadomości...
she asked me to come talk to her.
Miho poprosiła mnie o rozmowę.
Why?
Dlaczego?
She said, "Give me back Okazaki."
Powiedziała: „Oddaj mi Okazakiego”.
She killed herself because you refused?
Zabiła się, bo jej odmówiłaś?
Then, it really is your fault.
W takim razie to naprawdę twoja wina.
No, it's not.
Nie.
By that time,
Kiedy to się stało,
Okazaki and I had broken up.
Okazaki i ja już nie byliśmy razem.
What?
Co?
You broke up soon?
Tak szybko zerwaliście?
What the heck is with you?
Co jest z tobą nie tak?
Did you tell Miho that you had broken up?
Powiedziałaś Miho, że się rozstaliście?
Then,
Tak.
she asked why we broke up.
A ona zapytała o powód.
Quit crying! We can't hear you!
Przestań płakać! Trudno cię zrozumieć!
I broke up with Okazaki
Zerwałam z Okazakim...
because I found out his secret.
bo poznałam jego tajemnicę.
Secret?
Tajemnicę?
Okazaki
Okazaki...
caused someone to die because of a medical error.
popełnił błąd lekarski, w wyniku którego pacjent zmarł.
He said it was an accident, but...
Powiedział, że był to wypadek, ale...
he talked about it without any regret, so I became scared.
mówił o tym bez skruchy. Przestraszyłam się.
I also told Miho that that was the reason why we broke up.
Powiedziałam Miho, że to był powód naszego rozstania.
Then suddenly,
A ona nagle...
Miho started crying.
zaczęła płakać.
She committed suicide out of shock?
Tak nią to wstrząsnęło, że postanowiła się zabić?
That's pretty shocking, but...
To dość szokujące, ale...
Why would she die over that?
to jeszcze nie powód, żeby popełniać samobójstwo.
That's right.
Prawda.
Miho would never die over...
Miho nie zabiłaby się z powodu...
Oh, god! Is someone else going to vanish?
O nie! Czy któraś z nas zniknie?
I'm here! Kyoko is here, too!
Jestem tu! Kyoko też!
Shiho? Are you here, Shiho?
A Shiho? Jesteś tam, Shiho?
Of course not! She will be vanished for sure!
Oczywiście, że nie! To ona zniknie!
No!
Nie!
Sorry. It's just my phone.
Przepraszam, to mój telefon.
Don't scare me like that.
Nie strasz mnie.
What?
Co?
Shiho?
Shiho?
No way!
Niemożliwe!
Well, I'm glad we're all okay, but...
Dobrze, że nic nam nie jest, ale...
No!
Nie!
I saw someone's shadow at the skylight.
W świetliku mignął czyjś cień.
There's no way!
Niemożliwe!
I swear it!
Przyrzekam!
I saw a dark shadow, and the window was open.
Widziałam cień, a okno było otwarte.
You're kidding.
Żartujesz sobie.
Could it be
Myślicie,
Miho's ghost?
że to duch Miho?
I told you! She's not dead!
Mówiłam wam, ona nie umarła!
Is it going to be like this until morning?
Będziemy siedzieć po ciemku aż do rana?
I can't take it. I don't want to die here.
Nie wytrzymam. Nie chcę tu umrzeć.
I told you, don't say that stuff!
Mówiłam ci, żebyś nie mówiła o śmierci.
Are we all going to be killed?
Zabiją nas wszystkie?
Just calm down! We still don't know.
Uspokójcie się! Nic nie wiemy.
None of us has vanished. It could be a blackout.
Żadna z nas nie znikła. Może to przerwa w dostawie prądu.
Oh, that's right.
A właśnie.
Where is the lighter that Mana had?
Gdzie zapalniczka Many?
There, under that chair.
Tam, pod krzesłem.
Come to think of it,
Jak tak o tym pomyśleć...
there was a long blackout like this before.
już raz nie było prądu.
Oh, right. There was.
Faktycznie.
The whole town went dark.
W całym mieście było ciemno.
Even the traffic lights. It was scary.
Nie działała nawet sygnalizacja świetlna. To było straszne.
When did that happen?
Kiedy to było?
February 27.
Dokładnie 27 lutego.
You're probably right.
Chyba masz rację.
How did you remember that?
Czemu pamiętasz takie szczegóły?
Okazaki said his medical error was caused by a blackout.
Okazaki powiedział, że popełnił błąd przez awarię prądu.
Really?
Naprawdę?
In the confusion from the blackout, he got the wrong IV medicine.
Przez całe zamieszanie z awarią podał złą kroplówkę.
What? Really? That's scary.
Co? Naprawdę? To straszne.
But why would you give an IV when it's this dark?
Po co w ogóle podawał ją w ciemnościach?
Maybe it was an emergency, and he couldn't wait for the lights.
Może musiał działać szybko i nie mógł czekać.
Before the emergency lights came on,
Zanim włączyły się światła awaryjne...
the hospital was pitch black.
cały szpital był pogrążony w ciemnościach.
The doctors and nurses were in a huge panic.
Lekarze i pielęgniarki wpadli w panikę.
Of all the times, just then
I akurat wtedy...
a patient with asthma had an attack.
pacjent dostał ataku astmy.
He had to hurry and give them an IV.
Okazaki musiał szybko podać mu leki.
Okazaki had to do it all by himself.
Musiał zrobić to sam.
Really?
Naprawdę?
In the dark, the tray with the IVs on it fell over.
Ktoś w tych ciemnościach przewrócił tacę z kroplówkami.
He mistook an anesthetic for the asthma medicine.
Okazaki pomylił lek na astmę ze znieczuleniem.
-He didn't notice it. -No!
- Nie zauważył, że się pomylił. - Nie!
What?
Co?
Kumi?
Kumi?
No. It's not possible.
Nie, to niemożliwe.
Shiho.
Shiho?
The patient that Okazaki killed...
Pacjent, którego zabił Okazaki...
had asthma?
miał astmę?
Oh, god!
Nie!
No, it can't be!
To niemożliwe!
Kumi?
Kumi?
I realize
Wiem,
this may not be the time to ask this, but...
że to nie najlepszy moment...
You and Miho's best friend who died...
ale czy ta zmarła przyjaciółka twoja i Miho...
No!
Nie!
Mirei! What do you mean?
Mirei! Co masz na myśli?
Kumi.
Kumi.
I'm sorry.
Tak mi przykro.
Was the patient who died from Okazaki's mistake,
Czy z powodu błędu Okazakiego...
you and Miho's best friend?
zmarła przyjaciółka twoja i Miho?
Stop it!
Przestań!
Don't say that kind of thing!
Nie mów tak!
This can't be.
To niemożliwe.
Her boyfriend killed her best friend.
Chłopak Miho zabił jej przyjaciółkę.
If you realized that
Skoro domyśliłaś się tego
from what Shiho just said...
ze słów Shiho...
What?
Co?
You mean, Miho was so shocked, that she...
Miho musiała być w takim szoku, że...
But we can't tell it was her just from that!
Nie mamy pewności, czy to była ich przyjaciółka!
I don't know.
Nie wiem.
I didn't ask him who died!
Nie spytałam go, kto umarł.
If that's true, then Miho's suicide...
Jeśli to prawda, samobójstwo Miho...
Cut it out!
Przestań!
This is just crazy.
To szaleństwo.
Let's stop talking about this.
Nie mówmy już o tym.
But it's important to know if Miho killed herself or not.
Ale to ważne, żeby dowiedzieć się, czy Miho faktycznie się zabiła.
Why are you so cold?
Jak możecie?
You're blaming everything on Okazaki!
Zwalacie wszystko na Okazakiego!
All of you were bullying Miho, too!
Wszystkie nękałyście Miho!
Doesn't that bother you?
Jak możecie z tym żyć?
We may have driven her to do it.
Może to my ją do tego doprowadziłyśmy.
Kumi.
Kumi.
I'm really sorry.
Naprawdę mi przykro.
But you don't want to stay here, right?
Ale chcesz się stąd wydostać, prawda?
Then,
Więc...
when did that best friend die?
kiedy zginęła wasza przyjaciółka?
Earlier, you remembered exactly when that blackout was, right?
Pamiętałaś datę przerwy w dostawie prądu.
Shiho, can I see Kage's phone?
Shiho, podasz mi telefon Kage?
Just as I thought.
Tak jak myślałam.
"People who are doing what is right die,
„Dobrzy ludzie umierają,
but scumbags who should die go on living.
a śmiecie, które na to nie zasługują, żyją dalej.
It's an unjust world.
To niesprawiedliwy świat.
We'll change this rotten world. Perfect".
Naprawimy go. Idealna”.
I remember that.
Pamiętam to.
After this was posted,
Po tym poście
Perfect started going off the rails, though it was meant for doing right.
Idealna zmieniła podejście i zaczęła przeinaczać definicję dobra.
Kumi, do you remember when this was posted?
Kumi, pamiętasz datę tego wpisu?
Last year, on February 28th.
To było 28 lutego zeszłego roku.
The day after the blackout.
Dzień po awarii prądu.
Right.
Tak.
Answer me, Kumi!
Kumi, odpowiedz!
You're right.
Macie rację.
I got a call not long after that blackout.
Niedługo po awarii prądu dostałam telefon z informacją
They said she had died.
o jej śmierci.
But there's no way that Okazaki caused that!
Ale nie wierzę, że to wina Okazakiego!
I thought so, too.
Też tak myślałam.
I thought something must have happened during that blackout.
Myślałam, że coś się wtedy wydarzyło.
Miho thought the same thing.
Miho też tak sądziła.
But she was fooled by him.
Ale udało mu się ją oszukać.
Okazaki was...
Okazaki...
so kind in explaining what happened during the blackout at the hospital.
tak uprzejmie tłumaczył, co wtedy się wydarzyło.
So you backed down?
Więc odpuściłaś?
I mean, Miho said to forget it.
Miho kazała mi o tym zapomnieć.
She said she didn't want to cause her father or Okazaki any more trouble.
Powiedziała, że nie chce już sprawiać problemów ojcu ani Okazakiemu.
Miho really backed down after that?
Miho naprawdę się poddała?
But if the person you loved told you to believe him,
A co innego miała zrobić, skoro ukochana osoba...
what could you do, right?
poprosiła ją o zaufanie?
Right.
Racja.
If I hadn't opened my big mouth...
Gdybym tyle nie paplała...
You didn't know about that, Shiho.
Nie wiedziałaś o tym, Shiho.
But...
Ale...
What has happened with Okazaki anyway?
Co właściwie stało się z Okazakim?
Isn't he the one to blame?
Przecież to jego wina.
What?
Co?
-What's wrong, Shiho? -Water!
- Co się dzieje, Shiho? - Woda!
There's water!
Tu jest woda!
I knew it! It is Miho's curse!
Wiedziałam! To klątwa Miho!
I'm sorry, Miho! I'm really sorry!
Przepraszam, Miho! Naprawdę przepraszam!
Calm down! There's no such thing as a curse!
Uspokójcie się! Klątwy nie istnieją!
Shiho...
Shiho...
Miho...
Miho...
has cursed us and is killing us.
przeklęła nas i teraz zabija.
I told you, it's impossible!
Mówiłam ci, że to niemożliwe!
But if Miho really is dead, then who would do this?
Ale jeśli Miho rzeczywiście nie żyje, to kto za tym stoi?
There's still someone who could be behind this.
Chyba się domyślam.
If Miho really did kill herself,
Jeśli Miho naprawdę się zabiła...
then the person who locked us in here...
osobą, która nas tu zamknęła, jest...
THIS DRAMA IS A WORK OF FICTION.
PRZEDSTAWIONY SERIAL JEST FIKCJĄ.
Subtitle translation by Brian Athey
Napisy: Arianna Sugier